<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://bwurth.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://bwurth.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-05-10T18:44:27+00:00</updated><id>https://bwurth.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">INSIGHT - A Policy View on the Future of Entrepreneurial Ecosystem Research</title><link href="https://bwurth.github.io/posts/2024/insight-jbvi-paper/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="INSIGHT - A Policy View on the Future of Entrepreneurial Ecosystem Research"/><published>2024-05-01T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-05-01T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://bwurth.github.io/posts/2024/insight-jbvi-paper</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://bwurth.github.io/posts/2024/insight-jbvi-paper/"><![CDATA[<p><em>This post is based on research published in our paper “The future of entrepreneurial ecosystems research: Toward a policy-oriented research agenda” <a class="citation" href="#heswursta25">(Hess et al., 2025)</a>.</em></p> <hr/> <h2 id="beyond-that-dont-impress-me-much-making-entrepreneurial-ecosystem-research-matter-to-policymakers">Beyond “That Don’t Impress Me Much”: Making Entrepreneurial Ecosystem Research Matter to Policymakers</h2> <p>Have you ever enthusiastically shared your research insights with a policymaker only to be met with the academic equivalent of Shania Twain’s famous refrain: “That don’t impress me much”? This all-too-common experience highlights a growing disconnect between entrepreneurial ecosystem (EE) research and policy practice—a gap our recent paper in the Journal of Business Venturing Insights aims to address.</p> <h2 id="the-promise-and-challenge-of-entrepreneurial-ecosystem-research">The Promise and Challenge of Entrepreneurial Ecosystem Research</h2> <p>Entrepreneurial ecosystem research emerged with tremendous promise. Unlike earlier concepts focused purely on economic clustering or innovation systems, the EE approach distinctively emphasizes two critical aspects of entrepreneurship:</p> <ol> <li>Productive entrepreneurship as a key mechanism of economic development (building on Schumpeter and Baumol’s foundational work)</li> <li>Entrepreneurs themselves as central actors in ecosystem development (influenced by Brad Feld’s pioneering ideas)</li> </ol> <p>This dual emphasis represented a paradigm shift—suggesting a potential “privatization” of entrepreneurship policy and highlighting the power of bottom-up approaches. The concept’s intuitive appeal quickly captured the imagination of policymakers and researchers alike.</p> <p>Yet somewhere along the way, something went awry. As academics (myself included) worked to add theoretical complexity and rigor to the EE concept, we may have inadvertently reduced its clarity and actionability for policymakers. The result? In many regions, actual policies have outpaced their research foundations, leaving policymakers to design and implement EE initiatives without the evidence-based guidance research was supposed to provide.</p> <h2 id="a-collaborative-approach-to-bridge-the-gap">A Collaborative Approach to Bridge the Gap</h2> <p>To address this growing disconnect, we took an unusual approach to developing our paper. Rather than the traditional academic model of a few authors working in isolation, we engaged in what we call a “round-robin brainstorming” process involving 58 EE scholars from 21 countries at the 2024 EE Research Spring School in Stuttgart.</p> <p>This collaborative method allowed us to systematically gather diverse perspectives without letting any single voice dominate. The resulting insights were then validated and prioritized by European policymakers across various political jurisdictions to ensure our research agenda addressed genuine policy needs rather than merely academic interests.</p> <h2 id="reflecting-on-the-path-walked-evolution-of-the-ee-field">Reflecting on the Path Walked: Evolution of the EE Field</h2> <p>Our collective reflection revealed several key tensions in how the EE field has developed:</p> <h3 id="the-balancing-act-of-theory-and-practice">The Balancing Act of Theory and Practice</h3> <p>While academic research has made significant strides in identifying core elements of thriving ecosystems and broadening the scope of entrepreneurship policy, there has been a tendency to force various issues into the EE framework when other concepts might be more appropriate. Industrial clusters, regional innovation systems, and innovation districts all remain valuable frameworks depending on specific policy goals and regional contexts.</p> <p>A particular challenge has been the lack of clear boundary conditions—ambiguity around what constitutes an ecosystem, who should be included, and at what spatial level it should be analyzed. This ambiguity has led to difficulties in empirical work and policy implementation, especially since the fluid boundaries of ecosystems rarely align neatly with administrative boundaries where policies are typically formulated.</p> <h3 id="theoretical-development-beyond-borrowed-concepts">Theoretical Development: Beyond Borrowed Concepts</h3> <p>The EE field has predominantly built on imported theories—social capital theory, network theory, and complex systems theory. While these have yielded valuable insights, truly advancing policy-oriented research will require developing indigenous theories that fully embrace the complex, non-linear evolution of ecosystems and their place-dependent nature.</p> <p>A critical dimension often overlooked is time. Our analysis suggests that future theoretical development should incorporate three temporal aspects:</p> <ol> <li>The timing and alignment of key activities (market entries, funding cycles, product development phases) with broader economic cycles</li> <li>Non-linear dynamics and emergence, where small actions can have outsized impacts over time</li> <li>Long-term evolutionary dynamics of places that are missed when relying on short-term references</li> </ol> <h3 id="data-and-methods-the-need-for-methodological-pluralism">Data and Methods: The Need for Methodological Pluralism</h3> <p>Our collective analysis highlighted limitations in current research approaches. Quantitative studies have been largely cross-sectional, failing to capture the dynamic nature of EEs. Qualitative case studies, while valuable, often struggle to capture truly systemic views. And most studies focus on macro-level factors, potentially missing the proximate causes of ecosystem performance differences.</p> <p>Moving forward, we see tremendous opportunity in:</p> <ul> <li>Exploring and triangulating novel data sources across multiple levels of granularity</li> <li>Employing diverse methods including system dynamics, agent-based modeling, social network analysis, and AI</li> <li>Integrating research more directly into policy design processes through participatory approaches</li> </ul> <h2 id="a-policy-oriented-research-agenda-seeing-both-the-forest-and-the-trees">A Policy-Oriented Research Agenda: Seeing Both the Forest and the Trees</h2> <p>The heart of our paper proposes a structured research agenda organized around two key dimensions:</p> <ol> <li><strong>The policy process stages</strong>: design, implementation, monitoring and evaluation</li> <li><strong>The core analytical dimensions of the EE framework</strong>: context/structure and mechanisms/processes</li> </ol> <p>By mapping research questions to this framework, we can ensure that future research directly addresses the needs of policymakers while advancing theoretical understanding. From the twelve research questions we identified, policymakers prioritized three areas as particularly crucial:</p> <h3 id="1-establishing-ee-boundary-conditions-for-policy-design">1. Establishing EE Boundary Conditions for Policy Design</h3> <p>A pressing research need is understanding the role of different political jurisdictions (city, region, country) in ecosystem evolution. This includes addressing the complex challenges of multi-level governance and aligning capabilities, capacities, and funding structures across administrative boundaries.</p> <p>The research question driving this area: <strong>What is the role of different political jurisdictions in the evolution of EEs?</strong></p> <h3 id="2-understanding-connectivity-effects-in-policy-implementation">2. Understanding Connectivity Effects in Policy Implementation</h3> <p>Policymakers highlighted the critical importance of understanding how both intra-ecosystem connections (within an EE) and inter-ecosystem connections (between EEs) influence development. This includes addressing fragmented relationships among actors and reducing harmful competition between localities.</p> <p>The key research question here: <strong>How do intra- and inter-ecosystem linkages influence the development of EEs?</strong></p> <h3 id="3-expanding-metrics-for-effective-policy-evaluation">3. Expanding Metrics for Effective Policy Evaluation</h3> <p>Finally, policymakers emphasized the need for better data collection methods and more targeted measures for policy diagnostics and evaluation. This includes developing metrics that can justify investments in EE inputs and measure both short-term and long-term impacts.</p> <p>The central research question: <strong>How do novel methods and data enhance the capabilities for dynamic EE monitoring? What are the trade-offs between existing indicators and new measures?</strong></p> <h2 id="making-your-research-matter-a-call-to-action">Making Your Research Matter: A Call to Action</h2> <p>Rather than offering abstract ideas, our paper provides a concrete roadmap for producing research with genuine policy impact. I encourage you to use it in three ways:</p> <h3 id="1-as-a-diagnostic-tool">1. As a Diagnostic Tool</h3> <p>Bring the framework to a policymaker or entrepreneurship support organization in your region within the next month. Use it to start a conversation—and focus on listening rather than pushing your own ideas. Ask what challenges they face, what matters to them, and how your research might contribute.</p> <h3 id="2-as-a-dialogue-tool">2. As a Dialogue Tool</h3> <p>Organize an exchange that brings together researchers from different streams and unexpected guests like policymakers or ecosystem builders. Take inspiration from our round-robin process to mix expertise, challenge assumptions, and co-develop ideas that require more research attention.</p> <h3 id="3-as-a-design-tool">3. As a Design Tool</h3> <p>Take 15 minutes during your next break to reflect on your current projects: How might your new understanding of how policymakers leverage research insights reshape your research design or questions? How can you better address policy-relevant issues and contribute to one or more steps in the policy process?</p> <h2 id="beyond-academic-boundaries-the-value-of-collaborative-policy-oriented-research">Beyond Academic Boundaries: The Value of Collaborative Policy-Oriented Research</h2> <p>What made this project particularly rewarding was the genuine collaboration between researchers and policymakers. By engaging policymakers in validating and prioritizing our research agenda, we ensured that our academic work addressed real-world needs rather than merely advancing theoretical debates.</p> <p>This approach embodies what Van de Ven calls “engaged scholarship”—research that bridges the gap between theory and practice through meaningful dialogue with stakeholders. It recognizes that the most impactful research doesn’t just analyze from a distance but actively engages with the phenomena and people it studies.</p> <h2 id="conclusion-toward-transformational-impact">Conclusion: Toward Transformational Impact</h2> <p>The entrepreneurial ecosystem concept emerged with the promise of transforming entrepreneurship policy and practice. While it has made significant contributions, its full potential remains unrealized due to the growing disconnect between research and policy implementation.</p> <p>By adopting the policy-oriented research agenda we’ve proposed—focusing on boundary conditions, connectivity effects, and improved metrics—researchers can help close this gap. In doing so, we can ensure that EE research fulfills its original promise: providing actionable insights that help regions foster productive entrepreneurship and sustainable economic development.</p> <p>The future of entrepreneurial ecosystem research lies not just in refining concepts or debates within academic circles, but in developing insights that genuinely inform and transform policy and practice. Only then can we expect to hear policymakers say, “Now that does impress me much!”</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Insights"/><category term="Publication"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Read more about our new paper published in the Journal of Business Venturing Insights.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">INSIGHT - How Visual Imagery Shapes Collaborative Sensemaking in Entrepreneurial Ecosystems</title><link href="https://bwurth.github.io/posts/2024/insight-jbvi-paper/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="INSIGHT - How Visual Imagery Shapes Collaborative Sensemaking in Entrepreneurial Ecosystems"/><published>2024-03-01T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-01T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://bwurth.github.io/posts/2024/insight-jbvi-paper</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://bwurth.github.io/posts/2024/insight-jbvi-paper/"><![CDATA[<p><em>This post is based on research published in our paper “Beyond Words: How Visual Imagery Shapes Collaborative Sensemaking in Entrepreneurial Ecosystems” <a class="citation" href="#wurmaw24">(Wurth &amp; Mawson, 2024)</a>. The workshops that formed the basis for this paper were funded by the Scottish Government under the Scottish Tech Ecosystem Fund and in-kind support from the University of Strathclyde.</em></p> <hr/> <h2 id="introduction-when-pictures-help-us-see-the-bigger-picture">Introduction: When Pictures Help Us See the Bigger Picture</h2> <p>Have you ever found yourself in a room full of people discussing complex ideas, each person coming from a different background and speaking their own “language”? Now imagine that same room with a professional illustrator capturing those conversations in real-time, transforming abstract concepts into vivid visual representations. This is exactly what happened during our research into Scotland’s entrepreneurial ecosystem, and what we observed has profound implications for how we understand and develop these complex social systems.</p> <p>Entrepreneurial ecosystems are inherently complex - they bring together diverse actors from entrepreneurs and investors to policymakers and academics, each with their own perspectives, goals, and ways of understanding the world. The conventional wisdom suggests that simply bringing these people together will create connectivity and shared understanding. But our research suggests there’s a missing piece to this puzzle: the power of visual imagery to transform conversations into genuine collaborative sensemaking.</p> <h2 id="the-challenge-making-sense-together-in-complex-ecosystems">The Challenge: Making Sense Together in Complex Ecosystems</h2> <p>Before diving into our findings, let’s set the stage by understanding the fundamental challenge we’re addressing. Entrepreneurial ecosystems aren’t just collections of people and organizations - they’re intricate networks of relationships, shared meanings, and informal institutions that emerge through interaction and communication. The key word here is “shared.” For an ecosystem to function effectively, its participants need to develop common understandings of who they are, what they’re trying to achieve, and how they relate to each other.</p> <p>Think of it like trying to navigate a city without a map. Each person might know their immediate neighborhood well, but without a shared understanding of how these neighborhoods connect and relate to each other, movement and coordination become incredibly difficult. This is the challenge facing entrepreneurial ecosystems: how do we help diverse actors develop shared mental maps of their complex social environment?</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm-8 col-md-6 mt-3 mt-md-0 mx-auto"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/posts/2024-01-23_institutions_actors-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/posts/2024-01-23_institutions_actors-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/posts/2024-01-23_institutions_actors-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/posts/2024-01-23_institutions_actors.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Ecosystems, institutions, and the role of different actors <a class="citation" href="#wurmaw24">(Wurth &amp; Mawson, 2024)</a>. </div> <h2 id="beyond-verbal-communication-the-role-of-visual-imagery">Beyond Verbal Communication: The Role of Visual Imagery</h2> <p>Our research draws on the framework of communicative institutionalism, which suggests that institutions (the “rules of the game” that shape behavior) aren’t just reflected in communication - they’re actively created through it. While previous research has focused primarily on verbal communication - conversations, narratives, and stories - we discovered that visual imagery plays a crucial, and largely overlooked, role in this process.</p> <p>During a series of five workshops bringing together various ecosystem actors in Scotland, we employed a professional graphic illustrator to create real-time visual representations of the discussions. What started as an experiment in documentation quickly revealed itself to be something far more profound: the visuals weren’t just recording the conversations; they were actively shaping them.</p> <h2 id="three-key-discoveries-how-visuals-transform-ecosystem-conversations">Three Key Discoveries: How Visuals Transform Ecosystem Conversations</h2> <h3 id="1-broadening-participation-and-diverse-perspectives">1. Broadening Participation and Diverse Perspectives</h3> <p>One of the most striking observations was how visualizations helped surface and legitimize diverse perspectives within the ecosystem. In verbal discussions, dominant narratives often prevail - successful startups, major investors, and established institutions tend to command attention. But when these discussions were translated into visual imagery, something remarkable happened.</p> <p>For example, when participants began discussing who constitutes the entrepreneurial ecosystem, the conversation initially focused on the usual suspects: successful startups, universities, and support organizations. But as the illustrator began drawing, unexpected suggestions emerged. One particularly powerful moment came when someone mentioned prisons and the rehabilitation process as part of the ecosystem. The illustrator captured this idea visually, showing prisoners with entrepreneurial mindsets who hadn’t aligned their talents with society’s values and laws.</p> <p>This visual representation did more than just record an unusual suggestion - it legitimized it, made it tangible, and prompted deeper reflection from other participants. The image sparked discussions about inclusivity, overlooked potential, and the true boundaries of the ecosystem. By workshop three, the question had evolved from “who is part of the ecosystem?” to deeper considerations of belonging, voice, and creating environments where diverse actors can thrive.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/posts/2024-01-23_crop_inclusivity_1-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/posts/2024-01-23_crop_inclusivity_1-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/posts/2024-01-23_crop_inclusivity_1-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/posts/2024-01-23_crop_inclusivity_1.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/posts/2024-01-23_crop_inclusivity_2-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/posts/2024-01-23_crop_inclusivity_2-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/posts/2024-01-23_crop_inclusivity_2-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/posts/2024-01-23_crop_inclusivity_2.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Inclusivity and (informal) institutions in entrepreneurial ecosystems <a class="citation" href="#wurmaw24">(Wurth &amp; Mawson, 2024)</a>. </div> <h3 id="2-stimulating-metaphorical-associations">2. Stimulating Metaphorical Associations</h3> <p>Visuals also proved remarkably effective at creating and sustaining powerful metaphors that helped participants grasp complex concepts. Two metaphors in particular demonstrated this power:</p> <p>First, the concept of nested ecosystems - local systems within regional systems within national systems - was visualized using the metaphor of Russian Matryoshka dolls. This simple visual captured a complex idea about multi-level dynamics in a way that participants could immediately grasp and reference. More importantly, this metaphor became a shared reference point that persisted across workshops, helping new participants quickly understand previous discussions.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm-8 col-md-6 mt-3 mt-md-0 mx-auto"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/posts/2024-01-23_crop_nestedness-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/posts/2024-01-23_crop_nestedness-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/posts/2024-01-23_crop_nestedness-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/posts/2024-01-23_crop_nestedness.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Nestedness of entrepreneurial ecosystems <a class="citation" href="#wurmaw24">(Wurth &amp; Mawson, 2024)</a>. </div> <p>Second, the unicorn metaphor evolved throughout the workshops. Starting as the standard reference to billion-dollar startups, the visual representation transformed this into something deeper - a symbol of Scotland’s broader ambitions that integrated cultural narratives (the unicorn is Scotland’s national animal) with entrepreneurial aspirations. The continuous visual refinement of this metaphor helped participants move beyond simplistic success metrics toward more nuanced understandings of ecosystem goals.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/posts/2024-01-23_crop_unicorn_1-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/posts/2024-01-23_crop_unicorn_1-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/posts/2024-01-23_crop_unicorn_1-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/posts/2024-01-23_crop_unicorn_1.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/posts/2024-01-23_crop_unicorn_2-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/posts/2024-01-23_crop_unicorn_2-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/posts/2024-01-23_crop_unicorn_2-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/posts/2024-01-23_crop_unicorn_2.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> The unicorn depicted in various visual images, reflecting both Scotland and the ambition of entrepreneurship <a class="citation" href="#wurmaw24">(Wurth &amp; Mawson, 2024)</a>. </div> <h3 id="3-facilitating-alignment-on-shared-meanings">3. Facilitating Alignment on Shared Meanings</h3> <p>Perhaps most significantly, visuals helped participants align on shared meanings around fundamental concepts. Ecosystems, by their nature, involve complex feedback loops and dynamic interactions that are difficult to grasp through verbal description alone. When these concepts were visualized - using natural analogies of forests, rivers, and wildlife - abstract ideas became concrete and comprehensible.</p> <p>For instance, the visualization of entrepreneurs as differently sized fish in the same pond prompted recognition that ecosystem diversity equals ecosystem health. Similarly, depicting the government’s role in ecosystem development enabled more nuanced discussions about top-down versus bottom-up approaches. These weren’t just illustrations - they were thinking tools that enabled participants to explore complex relationships and dynamics.</p> <h2 id="practical-implications-moving-beyond-events-and-connectivity">Practical Implications: Moving Beyond Events and Connectivity</h2> <p>Our findings have significant implications for how we approach ecosystem development:</p> <h3 id="for-ecosystem-builders-and-policymakers">For Ecosystem Builders and Policymakers:</h3> <ol> <li> <p><strong>Incorporate visual practice:</strong> When organizing ecosystem events, workshops, or strategic planning sessions, consider incorporating professional graphic illustration or other visual methods. These aren’t just nice-to-have documentation tools - they’re active ingredients in fostering collaborative sensemaking.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Create sustained platforms:</strong> One-off events have limited impact. Create platforms that allow for iterative visual sensemaking over time, enabling narratives and understandings to evolve rather than crystallize prematurely.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Leverage visual ambiguity:</strong> Don’t aim for perfect clarity in visual representations. Some ambiguity can be generative, prompting deeper exploration and allowing multiple interpretations to coexist productively.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Bridge perspectives:</strong> Use visuals as boundary objects to help different ecosystem actors understand each other’s perspectives. Visual representations can make tacit assumptions explicit and create common ground for dialogue.</p> </li> </ol> <h3 id="for-researchers">For Researchers:</h3> <ol> <li> <p><strong>Expand methods:</strong> Consider how visual methods can complement traditional verbal data collection and analysis in studying entrepreneurial ecosystems and other complex social phenomena.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Study visual processes:</strong> Focus not just on the final visual artifacts but on the process of their creation and evolution. How do visuals emerge from and shape conversations over time?</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Connect to practice theory:</strong> Explore how visual practices become embedded in ecosystem routines and how they contribute to the embodiment of institutional logics.</p> </li> </ol> <h2 id="the-future-of-ecosystem-development-seeing-and-shaping-together">The Future of Ecosystem Development: Seeing and Shaping Together</h2> <p>As we look to the future of entrepreneurial ecosystem development, our research suggests that visual imagery should play a central role. We need to move beyond the assumption that simply bringing people together creates meaningful connection and shared understanding. Instead, we should create environments where diverse actors can literally see their thoughts, assumptions, and aspirations take shape together.</p> <p>The power of visual imagery lies not just in its ability to represent complex ideas, but in its capacity to transform how we think and interact. When we draw together, we think together. When we see our ideas visualized, we see new possibilities. And when we create shared visual languages, we create the foundation for genuine collaborative action.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm-8 col-md-6 mt-3 mt-md-0 mx-auto"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/posts/2024-01-23_crop_understanding_impact-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/posts/2024-01-23_crop_understanding_impact-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/posts/2024-01-23_crop_understanding_impact-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/posts/2024-01-23_crop_understanding_impact.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> A graphical representation of going from understanding EEs to thinking about collective, purposeful impact <a class="citation" href="#wurmaw24">(Wurth &amp; Mawson, 2024)</a>. </div> <h2 id="conclusion-drawing-our-way-to-better-ecosystems">Conclusion: Drawing Our Way to Better Ecosystems</h2> <p>Our research reveals that developing effective entrepreneurial ecosystems requires more than words - it requires ways of seeing and making sense together that transcend verbal communication. Visual imagery, when thoughtfully integrated into ecosystem conversations, can:</p> <ul> <li>surface and legitimize diverse perspectives,</li> <li>create powerful, persistent metaphors for complex concepts,</li> <li>facilitate alignment on shared meanings, and</li> <li>enable exploration of “distant futures” and alternative possibilities.</li> </ul> <p>As we continue to grapple with the complexity of entrepreneurial ecosystems, let’s remember that sometimes the most powerful conversations happen not just through what we say, but through what we draw, imagine, and visualize together. In the end, building better ecosystems might just require us to become better at seeing - and helping others see - the bigger picture.</p> <p>After all, when it comes to understanding complex social systems, a picture really can be worth a thousand words - or perhaps more accurately, a thousand conversations.</p> <hr/> <p><em>Below are the complete graphical illustrations (two per workshop) from which the excerpts for the paper were taken.</em></p> <swiper-container keyboard="true" navigation="true" pagination="true" pagination-clickable="true" pagination-dynamic-bullets="true" rewind="true"> <swiper-slide> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/scottish_ee_illustrations/week_01-01-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/scottish_ee_illustrations/week_01-01-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/scottish_ee_illustrations/week_01-01-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/scottish_ee_illustrations/week_01-01.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </swiper-slide> <swiper-slide> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/scottish_ee_illustrations/week_01-02-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/scottish_ee_illustrations/week_01-02-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/scottish_ee_illustrations/week_01-02-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/scottish_ee_illustrations/week_01-02.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </swiper-slide> <swiper-slide> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/scottish_ee_illustrations/week_02-01-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/scottish_ee_illustrations/week_02-01-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/scottish_ee_illustrations/week_02-01-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/scottish_ee_illustrations/week_02-01.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </swiper-slide> <swiper-slide> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/scottish_ee_illustrations/week_02-02-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/scottish_ee_illustrations/week_02-02-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/scottish_ee_illustrations/week_02-02-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/scottish_ee_illustrations/week_02-02.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </swiper-slide> <swiper-slide> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/scottish_ee_illustrations/week_03-01-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/scottish_ee_illustrations/week_03-01-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/scottish_ee_illustrations/week_03-01-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/scottish_ee_illustrations/week_03-01.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </swiper-slide> <swiper-slide> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/scottish_ee_illustrations/week_03-02-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/scottish_ee_illustrations/week_03-02-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/scottish_ee_illustrations/week_03-02-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/scottish_ee_illustrations/week_03-02.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </swiper-slide> <swiper-slide> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/scottish_ee_illustrations/week_04-01-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/scottish_ee_illustrations/week_04-01-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/scottish_ee_illustrations/week_04-01-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/scottish_ee_illustrations/week_04-01.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </swiper-slide> <swiper-slide> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/scottish_ee_illustrations/week_04-02-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/scottish_ee_illustrations/week_04-02-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/scottish_ee_illustrations/week_04-02-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/scottish_ee_illustrations/week_04-02.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </swiper-slide> </swiper-container> <p><em>You can also download the high-resolution version of each illustration here:</em></p> <p><a href="/assets/img/scottish_ee_illustrations/week_01-01.jpg" download="Workshop 1 - Illustration 1.jpg">Download Workshop 1 - Illustration 1</a> <br/> <a href="/assets/img/scottish_ee_illustrations/week_01-02.jpg" download="Workshop 1 - Illustration 2.jpg">Download Workshop 1 - Illustration 2</a> <br/> <a href="/assets/img/scottish_ee_illustrations/week_02-01.jpg" download="Workshop 2 - Illustration 1.jpg">Download Workshop 2 - Illustration 1</a> <br/> <a href="/assets/img/scottish_ee_illustrations/week_02-02.jpg" download="Workshop 2 - Illustration 2.jpg">Download Workshop 2 - Illustration 2</a> <br/> <a href="/assets/img/scottish_ee_illustrations/week_03-01.jpg" download="Workshop 3 - Illustration 1.jpg">Download Workshop 3 - Illustration 1</a> <br/> <a href="/assets/img/scottish_ee_illustrations/week_03-02.jpg" download="Workshop 3 - Illustration 2.jpg">Download Workshop 3 - Illustration 2</a> <br/> <a href="/assets/img/scottish_ee_illustrations/week_04-01.jpg" download="Workshop 4 - Illustration 1.jpg">Download Workshop 4 - Illustration 1</a> <br/> <a href="/assets/img/scottish_ee_illustrations/week_04-02.jpg" download="Workshop 4 - Illustration 2.jpg">Download Workshop 4 - Illustration 2</a> <br/></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Insights"/><category term="Publication"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Read more about our new paper published in the Journal of Business Venturing Insights.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">INSIGHT - A Systems Approach to Entrepreneurial Universities</title><link href="https://bwurth.github.io/posts/2024/insight-sbe-paper/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="INSIGHT - A Systems Approach to Entrepreneurial Universities"/><published>2024-01-23T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-01-23T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://bwurth.github.io/posts/2024/insight-sbe-paper</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://bwurth.github.io/posts/2024/insight-sbe-paper/"><![CDATA[<p><em>This post is based on research published in our paper “Not Seeing the Forest for the Trees? A Systems Approach to the Entrepreneurial University” <a class="citation" href="#wurmachow24">(Wurth et al., 2024)</a>.</em></p> <hr/> <h2 id="introduction-missing-the-forest-for-the-trees">Introduction: Missing the Forest for the Trees</h2> <p>In recent years, universities have been increasingly expected to contribute to economic development beyond their traditional missions of teaching and research. This has given rise to what we call the “entrepreneurial university” – institutions that engage in a wide range of activities from technology licensing and spin-offs to collaborative research and consulting with industry partners.</p> <p>As academics, we’ve studied these entrepreneurial activities extensively. Yet something has been missing in our approach. We’ve largely focused on individual activities, specific institutions, or isolated case studies – effectively examining the trees while missing the forest. In our recent paper <em>“Not Seeing the Forest for the Trees? A Systems Approach to the Entrepreneurial University,”</em> my colleagues Niall MacKenzie, Susan Howick, and I argue that we need a more holistic understanding of entrepreneurial universities that captures their inherent complexity and interconnectedness.</p> <h2 id="the-problem-with-current-research">The Problem with Current Research</h2> <p>The current academic literature suffers from three key limitations:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Isolated focus:</strong> Studies typically examine single activities (like licensing or spin-offs) without considering how they interact with other activities within the university.</li> <li><strong>De-contextualization:</strong> Research often fails to consider the broader ecosystem in which universities operate, treating them as isolated entities rather than parts of a larger system.</li> <li><strong>Static perspective:</strong> Most studies provide snapshot views rather than examining the dynamic evolution of entrepreneurial universities over time.</li> </ul> <p>The result is a fragmented understanding – what we refer to as “unit theories” of constituent parts without considering the wider feedback effects and implications. We’re looking at individual trees but missing how they form a complex, interconnected forest.</p> <h2 id="a-systems-thinking-approach">A Systems Thinking Approach</h2> <p>To address these limitations, we’ve developed what we call a “programmatic theory” of entrepreneurial universities using a systems thinking approach. Rather than focusing on isolated components, we’re examining how different activities, capabilities, and contextual factors interact and influence each other over time.</p> <p>Our research combines qualitative interviews with technology transfer office directors and staff from seven Scottish universities with quantitative data from various national surveys on university-industry interactions. We’ve synthesized these insights using causal loop diagrams (CLDs) – a tool from system dynamics that visualizes the interconnections and feedback loops within complex systems.</p> <h2 id="the-entrepreneurial-university-as-a-system-of-feedback-loops">The Entrepreneurial University as a System of Feedback Loops</h2> <p>So what does this systems perspective reveal? Let me walk you through some key insights from our model.</p> <h3 id="research-and-commercialization-dynamics">Research and Commercialization Dynamics</h3> <p>At the heart of our model is the relationship between research activities and commercialization. Universities conduct research, which can lead to discoveries and inventions. These may be disclosed to technology transfer offices, potentially leading to patents, licenses, and spin-off companies. The income generated from these activities is often reinvested into further research, creating a reinforcing loop.</p> <p>However, this is just the beginning. Our research shows that commercialization processes are far more complex than the linear models traditionally depicted in the literature. For instance, we found that only about a third of university spin-offs are based on disclosed and patented inventions. Many are created directly by academics without going through formal technology transfer mechanisms.</p> <h3 id="entrepreneurial-academics-as-key-agents">Entrepreneurial Academics as Key Agents</h3> <p>Our interviews revealed that most entrepreneurial activities involve a relatively small number of “entrepreneurial academics” – faculty members who actively seek opportunities to engage with industry partners. These individuals are crucial bridges between the university and external organizations.</p> <p>The total number of these entrepreneurial academics and their workload allocation define the “entrepreneurial capacity” of each university. When the amount of external engagement exceeds this capacity, universities face potential detrimental effects on their other missions. This creates balancing loops that limit growth unless universities can increase their entrepreneurial capacity. Reputation and Demand Dynamics</p> <p>Universities don’t operate in isolation – they’re embedded in ecosystems with various stakeholders, including industry partners. Our model shows how research prestige and entrepreneurial reputation influence industry demand for university collaboration.</p> <p>Companies typically follow a two-step decision process: first identifying a need for external input, then choosing their preferred academic partner. Research excellence attracts industry attention, but previous successful collaborations build entrepreneurial reputation, creating reinforcing loops that can accelerate future engagement.</p> <h3 id="supply-and-demand-stimulation">Supply and Demand Stimulation</h3> <p>Universities can grow their entrepreneurial activities through two main levers: internal supply stimulation and external demand stimulation.</p> <p>Internal stimulation involves increasing the number of entrepreneurial academics through incentives, skill development, and strategic hiring. External stimulation includes proactively engaging with industry, demonstrating expertise, and building relationships.</p> <p>Importantly, our research shows that universities must balance both approaches. Focusing on one at the expense of the other merely shifts the bottleneck rather than enabling sustainable growth.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm-8 col-md-6 mt-3 mt-md-0 mx-auto"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/posts/2024-03-01_cld_highlighted-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/posts/2024-03-01_cld_highlighted-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/posts/2024-03-01_cld_highlighted-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/posts/2024-03-01_cld_highlighted.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Complete causal-loop-diagram (CLD) with references to the aggregate themes from the interviews overlaid: ‘entrepreneurial academics’ (green), ‘supply stimulation’ (brown), ‘resource allocation according to university strategy’ (yellow), ‘reputation’ (orange), ‘partnerships’ (blue), and ‘demand stimulation’ (purple). <a class="citation" href="#wurmachow24">(Wurth et al., 2024)</a>. </div> <h2 id="practical-implications-lessons-for-universities-and-policymakers">Practical Implications: Lessons for Universities and Policymakers</h2> <p>What does this systems perspective mean for university leaders and policymakers? Here are some key takeaways:</p> <h3 id="for-university-leaders">For University Leaders:</h3> <ol> <li><strong>Recognize trade-offs:</strong> Increasing entrepreneurial activities without a balanced approach risks undermining other university missions. Our model helps visualize these potential trade-offs.</li> <li><strong>Develop dynamic capabilities:</strong> Universities need capabilities that allow them to sense changes in the environment and adapt accordingly. These go beyond static resources to include organizational learning and flexibility.</li> <li><strong>Cultivate partnerships, not just transactions:</strong> Long-term relationships with industry partners yield more value than one-off interactions. Universities should transition from a contractor mindset (offering “knowledge on a market basis”) to a partnership approach.</li> <li><strong>Balance supply and demand stimulation:</strong> Growing entrepreneurial activities requires both increasing internal capacity and generating external demand. Focusing on just one creates bottlenecks.</li> </ol> <h3 id="for-policymakers">For Policymakers:</h3> <ol> <li><strong>Look beyond commercialization:</strong> Policy support should extend beyond narrow metrics like patents and licenses to encompass the broader range of entrepreneurial activities.</li> <li><strong>Support capacity building:</strong> Effective policies must help universities develop the capabilities to manage complex entrepreneurial activities while maintaining excellence in teaching and research.</li> <li><strong>Treat university engagement as a “commons”:</strong> When universities actively engage with external organizations, they benefit the entire higher education sector by demonstrating the value of academic collaboration.</li> <li><strong>Consider systemic impacts:</strong> Our model helps policymakers anticipate how interventions might affect different parts of the system, potentially revealing unintended consequences.</li> </ol> <h2 id="the-value-of-systems-thinking-in-practice">The Value of Systems Thinking in Practice</h2> <p>Let me illustrate the practical value of this approach with an example from our research. One university we studied wanted to increase its industry engagement. Initial discussions focused on marketing and promotion strategies to attract more companies. However, our systems analysis revealed that entrepreneurial academics were already at full capacity.</p> <p>Without addressing this internal constraint, additional marketing would have created frustration as academics couldn’t take on more projects. By understanding the system as a whole, the university could develop a more balanced approach – gradually increasing academic capacity while strategically growing external demand.</p> <p>This example highlights why seeing both the forest and the trees matters. Understanding individual components (trees) is necessary but insufficient. We must also grasp how they interact within the broader system (forest).</p> <h2 id="future-research-directions">Future Research Directions</h2> <p>Our work opens several promising avenues for future research:</p> <ol> <li><strong>Methodological innovation:</strong> We need approaches that can capture feedback loops and interdependencies, such as system dynamics modeling and network analysis.</li> <li><strong>Data integration:</strong> Rather than creating new datasets for each study, researchers should combine existing data to gain more comprehensive insights.</li> <li><strong>Contextual variations:</strong> How do entrepreneurial university dynamics differ across geographic and institutional contexts?</li> <li><strong>Teaching-entrepreneurship connections:</strong> Future research should explore how teaching contributes to entrepreneurial universities, particularly in developing skills and entrepreneurial mindsets among graduates.</li> </ol> <h2 id="conclusion-embracing-complexity">Conclusion: Embracing Complexity</h2> <p>In conclusion, understanding entrepreneurial universities requires embracing complexity rather than avoiding it. Our systems approach offers a more holistic perspective that reconciles existing “unit theories” into a coherent programmatic theory.</p> <p>For university leaders, this perspective enables better strategic decision-making by helping diagnose capabilities and identify leverage points for improvement. For policymakers, it provides a framework for developing more effective support mechanisms that account for interdependencies and potential unintended consequences.</p> <p>By seeing both the forest and the trees, we can unlock the full potential of entrepreneurial universities to contribute to economic development and address societal challenges.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Insights"/><category term="Publication"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Read more about our new paper published in Small Business Economics.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Venturithm joins Strathclyde Inspire Accelerator</title><link href="https://bwurth.github.io/posts/2023/news-venturithm-inspire/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Venturithm joins Strathclyde Inspire Accelerator"/><published>2023-10-28T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-10-28T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://bwurth.github.io/posts/2023/news-venturithm-inspire</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://bwurth.github.io/posts/2023/news-venturithm-inspire/"><![CDATA[<p>Venturithm Ltd is proud to announce its acceptance into the <a href="https://www.strath.ac.uk/workwithus/strathclydeinspire/">University of Strathclyde Inspire</a> accelerator programme.</p> <p>This opportunity marks an exciting reunion with the University of Strathclyde, where I received my doctoral degreee and was a lecturer at the Hunter Centre for Entrepreneurship.</p> <blockquote> <p>“Joining the Inspire Accelerator is a full-circle moment for me. I have a deep personal connection to this institution, having been a PhD student and faculty member here. I am excited to build on that experience, coupled with fresh perspectives, and work with the team on taking Venturithm to the next level.” —Bernd Wurth</p> </blockquote> <hr/> <p>Strathclyde Inspire supports entrepreneurship in all its forms across the university’s ecosystem. For Strathclyde students, staff members, or alumni, there is support for:</p> <ul> <li>exploring your entrepreneurial potential, </li> <li>your idea for a business, or </li> <li>commercialising your research,</li> </ul> <p>through the four stages of Explore, Create, Launch, and Grow.</p> <p>Based in the heart of Scotland’s first Innovation District, GCID, the investor-ready <a href="https://www.strath.ac.uk/workwithus/strathclydeinspire/">Inspire Accelerator</a> welcomes participants on a rolling basis, ensuring you can fast-track your opportunity when the time is right. Over the course of 12-18 months, you will have access to a range of support including, but not limited to one-to-one advice; funding; bespoke training opportunities; regular cohort meetings; online presence; access to alumni, industry and partner networks; support from a virtual board; commercial champions; and pitching competitions.</p> <hr/> <p>For more information about Venturithm Ltd, its participation in the University of Strathclyde Inspire Accelerator programme, and everything else we are working on, please visit <a href="https://venturithm.com">https://venturithm.com</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="News"/><category term="Venturithm"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We are grateful for the support that will accelerate our product development and go-to-market.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">INSIGHT - Entrepreneurial Ecosystem Mechanisms</title><link href="https://bwurth.github.io/posts/2023/insight-fte-paper/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="INSIGHT - Entrepreneurial Ecosystem Mechanisms"/><published>2023-07-24T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-07-24T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://bwurth.github.io/posts/2023/insight-fte-paper</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://bwurth.github.io/posts/2023/insight-fte-paper/"><![CDATA[<p><em>This post is based on research published in our monograph “Entrepreneurial Ecosystem Mechanisms” <a class="citation" href="#wurstaspi23">(Wurth et al., 2023)</a>, which is an extension of our paper “Toward an Entrepreneurial Ecosystem Research Program” <a class="citation" href="#wurstaspi22">(Wurth et al., 2022)</a>.</em></p> <hr/> <h2 id="from-buzzword-to-research-program-understanding-how-entrepreneurial-ecosystems-work">From Buzzword to Research Program: Understanding How Entrepreneurial Ecosystems Work</h2> <p>Almost three years ago, my colleagues Erik Stam, Ben Spigel, and I published “<a href="https://berndwurth.com/posts/2021/insight-etp-paper/">Toward an Entrepreneurial Ecosystem Research Program</a>” in Entrepreneurship Theory and Practice. In that paper, we identified a paradox: the entrepreneurial ecosystem concept had become extremely popular among researchers, policymakers, and practitioners, yet remained theoretically underdeveloped and empirically fragmented.</p> <p>Since then, the field has continued to evolve rapidly. Our recent monograph, “Entrepreneurial Ecosystem Mechanisms,” published in Foundations and Trends in Entrepreneurship, builds on our earlier work and takes a deeper dive into the causal mechanisms that drive entrepreneurial ecosystems. We’ve expanded our systematic review to include 181 empirical studies (up from 62 in our previous work), providing the most comprehensive synthesis to date of what we actually know about how entrepreneurial ecosystems function.</p> <h2 id="the-mechanisms-framework-understanding-ecosystem-dynamics">The Mechanisms Framework: Understanding Ecosystem Dynamics</h2> <p>One of our core contributions is the development and refinement of a conceptual framework that identifies five key mechanisms explaining how entrepreneurial ecosystems work.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm-8 col-md-6 mt-3 mt-md-0 mx-auto"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/posts/2021-03-22_mechanisms-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/posts/2021-03-22_mechanisms-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/posts/2021-03-22_mechanisms-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/posts/2021-03-22_mechanisms.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Entrepreneurial ecosystem mechanisms <a class="citation" href="#wurstaspi22">(Wurth et al., 2022)</a>. </div> <h3 id="1-interdependence-of-ecosystem-elements">1. Interdependence of Ecosystem Elements</h3> <p>At the heart of our understanding of entrepreneurial ecosystems is the recognition that their elements—actors, resources, institutions, and connections—are deeply interdependent. This isn’t just a matter of co-location but reflects complex interactions and feedback loops among various components.</p> <p>In our expanded review, we found substantial empirical evidence that entrepreneurial ecosystems indeed function as complex adaptive systems. The elements interact in non-linear ways, creating feedback loops and co-evolutionary dynamics that extend beyond simple cause-and-effect relationships. As one study noted, “ecosystem configurations can vary significantly, and new policies or investments should develop support among underlying social and cultural attributes.”</p> <p>This interdependence manifests in several ways. For instance, universities adapt to the state of the ecosystem and contribute in multiple ways, often beyond their traditional remit of teaching and research. Similarly, entrepreneurial support organizations orchestrate collaborations beyond their regular realm, while “dealmakers” foster connectivity and knowledge spillovers within the ecosystem.</p> <p>Perhaps most importantly, we found that ecosystem elements are related in unique ways for every ecosystem. There is no one-size-fits-all configuration, which has significant implications for both research and policy.</p> <h3 id="2-upward-causation-from-ecosystem-to-outputs">2. Upward Causation: From Ecosystem to Outputs</h3> <p>The second mechanism explores how entrepreneurial ecosystems enable productive entrepreneurship—the outputs of the system. Initially, ecosystem research focused primarily on high-growth ventures, but our expanded review reveals a broadening scope to include social entrepreneurship, female entrepreneurship, and creative industries, among others.</p> <p>Different ecosystem configurations lead to different types of entrepreneurial outputs. For example, some ecosystems foster high-tech entrepreneurship while others support knowledge-intensive business services or social enterprises. Even within the same ecosystem, different “subsystems” can produce different outputs—a phenomenon increasingly recognized in the literature.</p> <p>Interestingly, while most studies show positive relationships between ecosystem quality and entrepreneurial outputs, there is also an emerging body of research questioning these links. Some studies find that entrepreneurial ecosystems, or at least many of their elements, have limited impact on entrepreneurial activity, particularly in remote or peripheral regions or for certain types of entrepreneurship.</p> <h3 id="3-upward-causation-from-outputs-to-outcomes">3. Upward Causation: From Outputs to Outcomes</h3> <p>Beyond producing entrepreneurial activity, ecosystems ultimately aim to drive broader economic and social outcomes. Our review shows growing evidence that entrepreneurial ecosystems foster economic growth through more efficient resource allocation and knowledge spillovers.</p> <p>However, this research reminds us that supporting the founding of high-potential startups is not enough—ecosystems must also support their growth, as the quality of entrepreneurship is more relevant than the quantity for economic development. Moreover, the quality or maturity of the entrepreneurial ecosystem matters, particularly at the regional level.</p> <p>Recent research has begun exploring broader socioeconomic benefits beyond traditional economic metrics. Entrepreneurial ecosystems have been linked to sustainable innovation, addressing grand societal challenges, and diverse social benefits including reduced crime and inequality.</p> <h3 id="4-downward-causation-and-path-dependencies">4. Downward Causation and Path Dependencies</h3> <p>The fourth mechanism recognizes that entrepreneurial ecosystems evolve over time, influenced by their own outputs and outcomes. This creates path dependencies—historical trajectories that shape current dynamics.</p> <p>Our expanded review provides stronger evidence for these feedback effects. Entrepreneurial output feeds back into the regional ecosystem, and individual entrepreneurs drive its evolution and resource dynamics. High-growth firms typically have a greater impact on the entrepreneurial ecosystem than new ventures in general.</p> <p>A particularly important process is entrepreneurial recycling, where successful entrepreneurs reinvest their wealth, knowledge, and connections back into the ecosystem. Local institutional structures support this recycling and mobility after external shocks, facilitating the re-entry of failed entrepreneurs as well.</p> <p>Interestingly, our review revealed gender differences in how entrepreneurs benefit from and contribute to ecosystems. The framework conditions of entrepreneurial ecosystems have different influences on the re-entry decisions of males and females who experience business failure, and women and men benefit in different ways from entrepreneurial ecosystems and their elements.</p> <h3 id="5-inter-ecosystem-links">5. Inter-Ecosystem Links</h3> <p>Finally, our framework recognizes that entrepreneurial ecosystems don’t exist in isolation. They’re connected to other ecosystems through the flow of people, ideas, and resources.</p> <p>Our expanded review, while still finding this to be the least-studied mechanism, provides stronger evidence that entrepreneurs, other ecosystem actors, and ideas move between ecosystems across spatial, cultural, and linguistic barriers. Transnational entrepreneurs play a key role in creating momentum and initiating institutional change in less-developed ecosystems. Even when returning to their home ecosystem, they continue to benefit from non-local connections in addition to their embeddedness in their home region.</p> <p>Digitalization also plays a role, helping entrepreneurial ecosystems overcome spatial barriers and increase access to resources beyond their boundaries. There are also spillover effects from large metropolitan centers to adjacent peripheral regions.</p> <h2 id="the-state-of-entrepreneurial-ecosystem-research">The State of Entrepreneurial Ecosystem Research</h2> <p>Beyond these five mechanisms, our monograph offers a comprehensive assessment of the current state of entrepreneurial ecosystem research. We analyzed 181 empirical studies published in top-tier journals, revealing several interesting patterns.</p> <p>The academic literature on entrepreneurial ecosystems has grown significantly since the mid-2010s, with research on interdependencies and ecosystem outputs dominating the field. There’s a noticeable lag in research on socioeconomic outcomes, downward causation, and inter-ecosystem links—likely due to the challenges of gathering longitudinal data and measuring broader impacts.</p> <p>Methodologically, we see a healthy diversity of approaches, with qualitative studies predominant in research on interdependencies and inter-ecosystem links, while quantitative approaches are more common in studies of outputs and outcomes. However, there’s still a bias toward European and North American contexts, leaving significant gaps in our understanding of entrepreneurial ecosystems in other parts of the world.</p> <h2 id="is-entrepreneurial-ecosystem-research-just-a-fad">Is Entrepreneurial Ecosystem Research Just a Fad?</h2> <p>In our analysis, we also confronted a critical question: Is the entrepreneurial ecosystem concept just a passing fad? Our answer is nuanced.</p> <p>Yes, there is intense enthusiasm for the concept, evidenced by the growing number of studies and policy initiatives. No, it’s not short-lived, as we’re witnessing continued growth over more than a decade.</p> <p>However, we found that out of 420 articles in high-quality journals claiming to conduct empirical entrepreneurial ecosystem research, the majority (56%) don’t actually engage with the core principles of entrepreneurial ecosystems as complex socioeconomic systems. Many use the term metaphorically or apply it to non-territorial units of analysis like organizations or platforms.</p> <p>This creates a risk that entrepreneurial ecosystem research becomes fashionable but superficial—a label to claim novelty without contributing to knowledge accumulation. As we note in the monograph, echoing findings in sustainability studies, there’s a lot of “scholarly bullshit” in so-called entrepreneurial ecosystem research.</p> <p>The good news is that there’s a substantial and growing amount of credible research, with the 181 empirical studies in our review providing a solid foundation for future work.</p> <h2 id="looking-forward-a-research-agenda">Looking Forward: A Research Agenda</h2> <p>Based on our comprehensive review, we propose several directions for future research:</p> <ol> <li> <p><strong>More relational studies</strong>: We need research that addresses “how” things happen within ecosystems, exploring novel data sources and non-standard methodological approaches.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Leadership in ecosystems</strong>: More in-depth and large-scale research into the nature, quality, and roles of leadership in entrepreneurial ecosystems is needed.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Stronger causality tests</strong>: Future studies should better test for causality, using (quasi) natural experiments or longitudinal data.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Beyond economic metrics</strong>: There’s a paucity of studies analyzing the effects of entrepreneurial ecosystems beyond traditional economic development measures.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Inter-ecosystem connections</strong>: More research on how entrepreneurs, ideas, and resources circulate between ecosystems, within and between countries, is essential.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Greater geographical diversity</strong>: More authorship and studies from beyond Europe and North America are needed to better understand entrepreneurial ecosystems in diverse contexts.</p> </li> </ol> <h2 id="implications-for-policy-and-practice">Implications for Policy and Practice</h2> <p>For policymakers and practitioners, our review offers several insights:</p> <ol> <li> <p><strong>Context matters</strong>: There is no one-size-fits-all approach to entrepreneurial ecosystem development. Policies must be tailored to the unique configuration of local ecosystems.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Quality over quantity</strong>: Supporting high-potential startups is not enough—ecosystems must also help them grow, as the quality of entrepreneurship is more important than quantity for economic development.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Systemic approach</strong>: Interventions should address the interdependence of ecosystem elements rather than focusing on isolated components.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Path dependencies</strong>: Policy should acknowledge historical trajectories and how the current state of the ecosystem affects the potential impact of interventions.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Beyond boundaries</strong>: Strategies should consider connections between ecosystems and how to foster beneficial flows of people, ideas, and resources.</p> </li> </ol> <p>By developing better data and knowledge about the nature and development of entrepreneurial ecosystems, stakeholders can conduct more effective diagnostics, prioritize policies more wisely, and better monitor and evaluate their impact.</p> <h2 id="conclusion-from-metaphor-to-mechanism">Conclusion: From Metaphor to Mechanism</h2> <p>The entrepreneurial ecosystem concept has evolved from a powerful metaphor to a substantive research program that enhances our understanding of entrepreneurship-led development and provides actionable knowledge for improving conditions for entrepreneurship.</p> <p>While we’ve made significant progress in identifying the causal mechanisms that drive entrepreneurial ecosystems, in many domains we’re still just scratching the surface of the empirical evidence needed for fully understanding their nature and development. More replication and extension studies are needed, as well as research that fills the voids in our knowledge base.</p> <p>The value of the entrepreneurial ecosystem approach lies not in its popularity as a buzzword but in its ability to generate insights that can improve both research and practice. By focusing on rigorous empirical investigation of the mechanisms that drive ecosystem dynamics, we can move beyond metaphorical uses of the concept toward a more substantive and useful understanding of how entrepreneurial ecosystems actually work.</p> <p>As we conclude in our monograph, “Only in this way can we improve each entrepreneurial ecosystem in its own right, acknowledging and building on place-specific heritage, and make the transdisciplinary entrepreneurial ecosystem research program work.”</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Insights"/><category term="Publication"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Read more about our new paper published in Foundations and Trends in Entrepreneurship.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">INSIGHT - Toward an Entrepreneurial Ecosystem Research Program</title><link href="https://bwurth.github.io/posts/2021/insight-etp-paper/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="INSIGHT - Toward an Entrepreneurial Ecosystem Research Program"/><published>2021-03-22T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-03-22T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://bwurth.github.io/posts/2021/insight-etp-paper</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://bwurth.github.io/posts/2021/insight-etp-paper/"><![CDATA[<p><em>This post is based on research published in our paper “Toward an Entrepreneurial Ecosystem Research Program” <a class="citation" href="#wurstaspi22">(Wurth et al., 2022)</a>.</em></p> <hr/> <h2 id="introduction-beyond-the-buzzword">Introduction: Beyond the Buzzword</h2> <p>Over the past decade, the concept of “entrepreneurial ecosystems” has exploded in popularity among researchers, policymakers, and practitioners. From Silicon Valley to Singapore, the idea of creating supportive regional environments for innovative entrepreneurs has captured imaginations worldwide. But in many ways, the entrepreneurial ecosystem concept represents a paradox: it’s simultaneously one of the most influential frameworks in contemporary entrepreneurship policy while remaining theoretically underdeveloped and empirically fragmented.</p> <p>My colleagues Erik Stam, Ben Spigel, and I recognized this tension. While the concept draws on rich intellectual traditions and offers real potential to unite disparate research streams, it often lacks precise theoretical grounding and empirical validation. In our paper “Toward an Entrepreneurial Ecosystem Research Program,” published in Entrepreneurship Theory and Practice, we decided to take stock of the growing entrepreneurial ecosystem literature to identify what we actually know about how these systems work, and where more research is needed.</p> <h2 id="the-promise-and-paradox-of-entrepreneurial-ecosystems">The Promise and Paradox of Entrepreneurial Ecosystems</h2> <p>What makes the entrepreneurial ecosystem concept distinctive from earlier approaches to regional economic development? We identified two key advances:</p> <ol> <li> <p><strong>A focus on productive entrepreneurship</strong>: Unlike earlier work on regional innovation systems or clusters that focused on all forms of business activity, the ecosystem approach specifically targets entrepreneurship that contributes to net economic output—typically high-growth ventures, innovative startups, and entrepreneurial employees that drive productivity gains.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Emphasis on entrepreneurial agency</strong>: Ecosystem approaches foreground the role of entrepreneurs themselves as organizational and community leaders who can shape their environments, not just passive recipients of structural conditions.</p> </li> </ol> <p>These advances represent a significant shift in how we understand regional economic development. Rather than viewing entrepreneurship as something that happens within broader economic structures, the ecosystem perspective puts entrepreneurs at the center, exploring how their agency interacts with and transforms social and economic structures.</p> <p>But despite these promising theoretical foundations, ecosystem research faces several challenges. Through our systematic review of the literature, we found that studies often use the ecosystem concept merely metaphorically without engaging with its core principles of interdependence. Many studies focus on isolated elements rather than examining the system as a whole. And there’s considerable confusion about what constitutes an ecosystem, where its boundaries lie, and how to measure its performance.</p> <h2 id="what-we-know-causal-mechanisms-in-entrepreneurial-ecosystems">What We Know: Causal Mechanisms in Entrepreneurial Ecosystems</h2> <p>One of our key contributions is synthesizing the empirical evidence on the causal mechanisms that drive entrepreneurial ecosystems. Based on our review of the literature, we identified five key causal mechanisms.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm-8 col-md-6 mt-3 mt-md-0 mx-auto"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/posts/2021-03-22_mechanisms-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/posts/2021-03-22_mechanisms-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/posts/2021-03-22_mechanisms-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/posts/2021-03-22_mechanisms.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Entrepreneurial ecosystem mechanisms <a class="citation" href="#wurstaspi22">(Wurth et al., 2022)</a>. </div> <h3 id="1-interdependence-of-elements">1. Interdependence of Elements</h3> <p>Perhaps the most fundamental characteristic of ecosystems is the interdependence between different elements. Our review shows that research consistently finds that ecosystem elements are uniquely related in each ecosystem, with feedback and (non-linear) co-evolutionary dynamics between elements themselves and with the wider socio-economic context. This isn’t just theoretical—it has practical implications. Many innovation and entrepreneurship policies fail precisely because they invest in isolated elements (like physical infrastructure) without supporting the underlying cultural and social attributes needed for success.</p> <p>Individual actors play crucial roles in fostering this connectivity. Universities, for example, often adapt to the state of the ecosystem and contribute in multiple ways beyond their traditional teaching and research roles. Anchor organizations (like established firms or research institutions) frequently initiate and support the initial growth of ecosystems. These interactions aren’t static—governance typically changes from hierarchical to relational as the ecosystem evolves, and the roles of different actors and support organizations evolve alongside the ecosystem itself.</p> <h3 id="2-links-to-entrepreneurial-outputs">2. Links to Entrepreneurial Outputs</h3> <p>Different ecosystem configurations produce different types of entrepreneurial activity. Even within a single ecosystem, there can be various subclusters based on organizational and individual-level factors. Research has identified distinct institutional settings that enable different types of entrepreneurship, from high-tech ventures to more traditional businesses.</p> <p>Intriguingly, women and men appear to benefit in different ways from ecosystems and their elements. Globally, women often benefit more from many ecosystem factors than men, though this varies depending on the phase of economic development. Women tend to mobilize more resources than men to overcome support constraints, while men generally report higher confidence in their capabilities.</p> <p>Most studies find that ecosystems provide the foundation for high-tech entrepreneurship, with cultural and social norms, government programs, and internal market dynamics being particularly important for enabling high-growth startups. The overall quality of an ecosystem is positively related to entrepreneurial output, and ventures in high-performance ecosystems tend to perform better and have higher survival chances.</p> <h3 id="3-links-to-economic-outcomes">3. Links to Economic Outcomes</h3> <p>Beyond producing entrepreneurial activity, ecosystems ultimately aim to drive broader economic and social outcomes. Several studies have shown that ecosystem quality at the country level is linked to economic growth. Mature ecosystems enable knowledge spillovers, which increase efficient resource allocation and contribute to national productivity by promoting both Kirznerian and Schumpeterian forms of entrepreneurship.</p> <p>There appears to be a positive impact from the interaction between companies, universities, and government on entrepreneurial development, with this effect being greater for more developed regions and ecosystems. Importantly, ecosystems seem to moderate the relationship between entrepreneurship and regional economic growth—the same entrepreneurial activity can produce very different economic outcomes depending on the quality of the surrounding ecosystem.</p> <h3 id="4-path-dependency-and-downward-causation">4. Path Dependency and Downward Causation</h3> <p>Entrepreneurial ecosystems aren’t just influenced by their elements—they’re also shaped by their own history and past performance. Individual ecosystems are unique due to their historical, cultural, and institutional heritage. There’s strong path dependence in the evolution of entrepreneurial ecosystems, as entrepreneurial output feeds back into the regional ecosystem.</p> <p>The broader economic development of a country shapes its ecosystems, and high-growth firms appear to have a greater impact on the entrepreneurial ecosystem than new ventures in general. The state of the ecosystem also influences whether entrepreneurs choose to come to or stay in a region to start a new tech venture.</p> <p>In less mature ecosystems, for instance, only more mature startups tend to apply for angel investment, whereas in more developed ecosystems, earlier-stage ventures also seek this funding. Policy interventions need to account for the current state of the ecosystem, as they can have different effects on involved clusters and industries depending on the ecosystem’s development stage.</p> <h3 id="5-links-between-ecosystems">5. Links Between Ecosystems</h3> <p>Finally, ecosystems don’t exist in isolation—they’re connected to other ecosystems through various channels. Research shows that ecosystems are part of wider transnational social fields shaped by the circulation of actors, ideologies, texts, and objects. Emigration, return migration, and outmigration all influence the emergence and evolution of ecosystems.</p> <p>Contrary to how they’re often portrayed, entrepreneurial ecosystems aren’t static, bounded entities mapped neatly onto a city or nation—they’re dynamic, changing, and densely connected with other systems across both near and distant spaces. There’s bi-directional learning between migrant entrepreneurs and ecosystems, as entrepreneurs bring knowledge and practices from one ecosystem to another.</p> <h2 id="the-way-forward-a-transdisciplinary-research-program">The Way Forward: A Transdisciplinary Research Program</h2> <p>Based on our synthesis of the literature, we propose a comprehensive research program to advance our understanding of entrepreneurial ecosystems. This program consists of four main research streams and four cross-cutting themes.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm-8 col-md-6 mt-3 mt-md-0 mx-auto"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/posts/2021-03-22_research_program-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/posts/2021-03-22_research_program-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/posts/2021-03-22_research_program-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/posts/2021-03-22_research_program.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Entrepreneurial ecosystem research program with four research streams (horizontal) and four cross-sectional themes (vertical) <a class="citation" href="#wurstaspi22">(Wurth et al., 2022)</a>. </div> <h3 id="research-streams">Research Streams</h3> <ol> <li> <p><strong>Context</strong>: Examining how ecosystems are embedded in broader social, economic, and political contexts, and how these contexts shape ecosystem development and performance.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Structure</strong>: Exploring the networks and connections that enable resources, knowledge, and support to flow within ecosystems.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Microfoundations</strong>: Investigating the processes at the micro-level that drive ecosystem development, including how individual entrepreneurs and organizations interact and co-evolve.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Complex Systems</strong>: Applying complex systems approaches to better understand the non-linear dynamics, emergence, and resilience of entrepreneurial ecosystems.</p> </li> </ol> <h3 id="cross-cutting-themes">Cross-Cutting Themes</h3> <ol> <li> <p><strong>Methodologies and Measurements</strong>: Developing new ways to study and measure entrepreneurial ecosystems beyond the current reliance on case studies and cross-sectional analyses.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Theory</strong>: Strengthening the theoretical foundations of ecosystem research by integrating insights from institutional theory, evolutionary approaches, social capital theory, and complex systems thinking.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Critical Research</strong>: Questioning the implicit assumptions and potential negative consequences of entrepreneurial ecosystem policies, including issues of inclusion, equality, and sustainability.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Transdisciplinary Research</strong>: Moving from research on ecosystems to research for ecosystems, integrating academic knowledge with practical insights to develop more effective interventions.</p> </li> </ol> <h2 id="implications-for-research-policy-and-practice">Implications for Research, Policy, and Practice</h2> <p>Our review and proposed research program have significant implications for different stakeholders in the entrepreneurial ecosystem field:</p> <h3 id="for-researchers">For Researchers</h3> <p>Our work highlights the need to move beyond the metaphorical use of the ecosystem concept toward more rigorous theoretical and empirical approaches. This means:</p> <ul> <li>Developing more sophisticated methodologies that can capture the complex, dynamic nature of ecosystems, including longitudinal studies, mixed methods, and simulation approaches</li> <li>Focusing on the interconnections between ecosystem elements rather than studying elements in isolation</li> <li>Considering the multicscalar nature of ecosystems, from local to global</li> <li>Integrating insights from diverse theoretical traditions, from institutional theory to complex systems thinking</li> </ul> <h3 id="for-policymakers">For Policymakers</h3> <p>Our findings suggest that effective ecosystem policies need to:</p> <ul> <li>Address the interdependence of ecosystem elements rather than focusing on isolated interventions</li> <li>Recognize that different ecosystem configurations may be needed for different types of entrepreneurship</li> <li>Acknowledge path dependencies and consider how the current state of the ecosystem affects the potential impact of interventions</li> <li>Be sensitive to local contexts and avoid simply copying features from successful regions</li> <li>Consider the potential negative consequences of ecosystem development, including issues of inclusion and equality</li> </ul> <h3 id="for-practitioners">For Practitioners</h3> <p>Entrepreneurs and other ecosystem actors can benefit from our work by:</p> <ul> <li>Understanding how their activities contribute to the broader ecosystem</li> <li>Recognizing the importance of connections and relationships in accessing resources and support</li> <li>Appreciating how the quality of the surrounding ecosystem affects venture performance and growth potential</li> <li>Considering how they can participate in shaping their ecosystem through both individual and collective actions</li> </ul> <h2 id="conclusion-from-buzzword-to-research-program">Conclusion: From Buzzword to Research Program</h2> <p>The entrepreneurial ecosystem concept has come a long way from its origins in practitioner-oriented publications like Brad Feld’s “Startup Communities” and Daniel Isenberg’s Harvard Business Review articles. It now represents one of the most influential frameworks in entrepreneurship research and policy.</p> <p>Yet to fulfill its potential, the concept needs to move beyond its current state as a popular but undertheorized buzzword. By synthesizing the empirical evidence on how ecosystems work and proposing a comprehensive research program, we hope to contribute to this transition. The entrepreneurial ecosystem approach offers a promising way to integrate insights from various research traditions and to bridge the gap between structure and agency in understanding entrepreneurial activity.</p> <p>As the field continues to evolve, we need to maintain a critical perspective, questioning both theoretical assumptions and policy implications. But with a more rigorous and nuanced understanding of how entrepreneurial ecosystems function, we can develop more effective approaches to supporting the kinds of entrepreneurship that contribute to economic development and societal well-being.</p> <p>After all, entrepreneurship doesn’t happen in a vacuum—it emerges from and contributes to complex social, economic, and institutional environments. By better understanding these environments, we can better understand and support entrepreneurship itself.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Insights"/><category term="Publication"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Read more about our new paper published in Entrepreneurship Theory and Practice.]]></summary></entry></feed>