<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://bwurth.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://bwurth.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-04-26T20:34:54+00:00</updated><id>https://bwurth.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">INSIGHT - How Visual Imagery Shapes Collaborative Sensemaking in Entrepreneurial Ecosystems</title><link href="https://bwurth.github.io/posts/2024/insight-jbvi-paper/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="INSIGHT - How Visual Imagery Shapes Collaborative Sensemaking in Entrepreneurial Ecosystems"/><published>2024-03-01T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-01T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://bwurth.github.io/posts/2024/insight-jbvi-paper</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://bwurth.github.io/posts/2024/insight-jbvi-paper/"><![CDATA[<p><em>This post is based on research published in our paper “Beyond Words: How Visual Imagery Shapes Collaborative Sensemaking in Entrepreneurial Ecosystems” <a class="citation" href="#wurmaw24">(Wurth &amp; Mawson, 2024)</a>. The workshops that formed the basis for this paper were funded by the Scottish Government under the Scottish Tech Ecosystem Fund and in-kind support from the University of Strathclyde.</em></p> <hr/> <h2 id="introduction-when-pictures-help-us-see-the-bigger-picture">Introduction: When Pictures Help Us See the Bigger Picture</h2> <p>Have you ever found yourself in a room full of people discussing complex ideas, each person coming from a different background and speaking their own “language”? Now imagine that same room with a professional illustrator capturing those conversations in real-time, transforming abstract concepts into vivid visual representations. This is exactly what happened during our research into Scotland’s entrepreneurial ecosystem, and what we observed has profound implications for how we understand and develop these complex social systems.</p> <p>Entrepreneurial ecosystems are inherently complex - they bring together diverse actors from entrepreneurs and investors to policymakers and academics, each with their own perspectives, goals, and ways of understanding the world. The conventional wisdom suggests that simply bringing these people together will create connectivity and shared understanding. But our research suggests there’s a missing piece to this puzzle: the power of visual imagery to transform conversations into genuine collaborative sensemaking.</p> <h2 id="the-challenge-making-sense-together-in-complex-ecosystems">The Challenge: Making Sense Together in Complex Ecosystems</h2> <p>Before diving into our findings, let’s set the stage by understanding the fundamental challenge we’re addressing. Entrepreneurial ecosystems aren’t just collections of people and organizations - they’re intricate networks of relationships, shared meanings, and informal institutions that emerge through interaction and communication. The key word here is “shared.” For an ecosystem to function effectively, its participants need to develop common understandings of who they are, what they’re trying to achieve, and how they relate to each other.</p> <p>Think of it like trying to navigate a city without a map. Each person might know their immediate neighborhood well, but without a shared understanding of how these neighborhoods connect and relate to each other, movement and coordination become incredibly difficult. This is the challenge facing entrepreneurial ecosystems: how do we help diverse actors develop shared mental maps of their complex social environment?</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/posts/2024-01-23_institutions_actors-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/posts/2024-01-23_institutions_actors-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/posts/2024-01-23_institutions_actors-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/posts/2024-01-23_institutions_actors" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Ecosystems, institutions, and the role of different actors <a class="citation" href="#wurmaw24">(Wurth &amp; Mawson, 2024)</a>. </div> <h2 id="beyond-verbal-communication-the-role-of-visual-imagery">Beyond Verbal Communication: The Role of Visual Imagery</h2> <p>Our research draws on the framework of communicative institutionalism, which suggests that institutions (the “rules of the game” that shape behavior) aren’t just reflected in communication - they’re actively created through it. While previous research has focused primarily on verbal communication - conversations, narratives, and stories - we discovered that visual imagery plays a crucial, and largely overlooked, role in this process.</p> <p>During a series of five workshops bringing together various ecosystem actors in Scotland, we employed a professional graphic illustrator to create real-time visual representations of the discussions. What started as an experiment in documentation quickly revealed itself to be something far more profound: the visuals weren’t just recording the conversations; they were actively shaping them.</p> <h2 id="three-key-discoveries-how-visuals-transform-ecosystem-conversations">Three Key Discoveries: How Visuals Transform Ecosystem Conversations</h2> <h3 id="1-broadening-participation-and-diverse-perspectives">1. Broadening Participation and Diverse Perspectives</h3> <p>One of the most striking observations was how visualizations helped surface and legitimize diverse perspectives within the ecosystem. In verbal discussions, dominant narratives often prevail - successful startups, major investors, and established institutions tend to command attention. But when these discussions were translated into visual imagery, something remarkable happened.</p> <p>For example, when participants began discussing who constitutes the entrepreneurial ecosystem, the conversation initially focused on the usual suspects: successful startups, universities, and support organizations. But as the illustrator began drawing, unexpected suggestions emerged. One particularly powerful moment came when someone mentioned prisons and the rehabilitation process as part of the ecosystem. The illustrator captured this idea visually, showing prisoners with entrepreneurial mindsets who hadn’t aligned their talents with society’s values and laws.</p> <p>This visual representation did more than just record an unusual suggestion - it legitimized it, made it tangible, and prompted deeper reflection from other participants. The image sparked discussions about inclusivity, overlooked potential, and the true boundaries of the ecosystem. By workshop three, the question had evolved from “who is part of the ecosystem?” to deeper considerations of belonging, voice, and creating environments where diverse actors can thrive.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/posts/2024-01-23-crop_inclusivity_1-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/posts/2024-01-23-crop_inclusivity_1-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/posts/2024-01-23-crop_inclusivity_1-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/posts/2024-01-23-crop_inclusivity_1.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/posts/2024-01-23-crop_inclusivity_2-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/posts/2024-01-23-crop_inclusivity_2-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/posts/2024-01-23-crop_inclusivity_2-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/posts/2024-01-23-crop_inclusivity_2.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Inclusivity and (informal) institutions in entrepreneurial ecosystems <a class="citation" href="#wurmaw24">(Wurth &amp; Mawson, 2024)</a>. </div> <h3 id="2-stimulating-metaphorical-associations">2. Stimulating Metaphorical Associations</h3> <p>Visuals also proved remarkably effective at creating and sustaining powerful metaphors that helped participants grasp complex concepts. Two metaphors in particular demonstrated this power:</p> <p>First, the concept of nested ecosystems - local systems within regional systems within national systems - was visualized using the metaphor of Russian Matryoshka dolls. This simple visual captured a complex idea about multi-level dynamics in a way that participants could immediately grasp and reference. More importantly, this metaphor became a shared reference point that persisted across workshops, helping new participants quickly understand previous discussions.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/posts/2024-01-23_crop_nestedness-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/posts/2024-01-23_crop_nestedness-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/posts/2024-01-23_crop_nestedness-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/posts/2024-01-23_crop_nestedness.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Nestedness of entrepreneurial ecosystems <a class="citation" href="#wurmaw24">(Wurth &amp; Mawson, 2024)</a>. </div> <p>Second, the unicorn metaphor evolved throughout the workshops. Starting as the standard reference to billion-dollar startups, the visual representation transformed this into something deeper - a symbol of Scotland’s broader ambitions that integrated cultural narratives (the unicorn is Scotland’s national animal) with entrepreneurial aspirations. The continuous visual refinement of this metaphor helped participants move beyond simplistic success metrics toward more nuanced understandings of ecosystem goals.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/posts/2024-01-23-crop_unicorn_1-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/posts/2024-01-23-crop_unicorn_1-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/posts/2024-01-23-crop_unicorn_1-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/posts/2024-01-23-crop_unicorn_1.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/posts/2024-01-23-crop_unicorn_2-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/posts/2024-01-23-crop_unicorn_2-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/posts/2024-01-23-crop_unicorn_2-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/posts/2024-01-23-crop_unicorn_2.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> The unicorn depicted in various visual images, reflecting both Scotland and the ambition of entrepreneurship <a class="citation" href="#wurmaw24">(Wurth &amp; Mawson, 2024)</a>. </div> <h3 id="3-facilitating-alignment-on-shared-meanings">3. Facilitating Alignment on Shared Meanings</h3> <p>Perhaps most significantly, visuals helped participants align on shared meanings around fundamental concepts. Ecosystems, by their nature, involve complex feedback loops and dynamic interactions that are difficult to grasp through verbal description alone. When these concepts were visualized - using natural analogies of forests, rivers, and wildlife - abstract ideas became concrete and comprehensible.</p> <p>For instance, the visualization of entrepreneurs as differently sized fish in the same pond prompted recognition that ecosystem diversity equals ecosystem health. Similarly, depicting the government’s role in ecosystem development enabled more nuanced discussions about top-down versus bottom-up approaches. These weren’t just illustrations - they were thinking tools that enabled participants to explore complex relationships and dynamics.</p> <h2 id="practical-implications-moving-beyond-events-and-connectivity">Practical Implications: Moving Beyond Events and Connectivity</h2> <p>Our findings have significant implications for how we approach ecosystem development:</p> <h3 id="for-ecosystem-builders-and-policymakers">For Ecosystem Builders and Policymakers:</h3> <ol> <li> <p><strong>Incorporate visual practice:</strong> When organizing ecosystem events, workshops, or strategic planning sessions, consider incorporating professional graphic illustration or other visual methods. These aren’t just nice-to-have documentation tools - they’re active ingredients in fostering collaborative sensemaking.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Create sustained platforms:</strong> One-off events have limited impact. Create platforms that allow for iterative visual sensemaking over time, enabling narratives and understandings to evolve rather than crystallize prematurely.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Leverage visual ambiguity:</strong> Don’t aim for perfect clarity in visual representations. Some ambiguity can be generative, prompting deeper exploration and allowing multiple interpretations to coexist productively.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Bridge perspectives:</strong> Use visuals as boundary objects to help different ecosystem actors understand each other’s perspectives. Visual representations can make tacit assumptions explicit and create common ground for dialogue.</p> </li> </ol> <h3 id="for-researchers">For Researchers:</h3> <ol> <li> <p><strong>Expand methods:</strong> Consider how visual methods can complement traditional verbal data collection and analysis in studying entrepreneurial ecosystems and other complex social phenomena.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Study visual processes:</strong> Focus not just on the final visual artifacts but on the process of their creation and evolution. How do visuals emerge from and shape conversations over time?</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Connect to practice theory:</strong> Explore how visual practices become embedded in ecosystem routines and how they contribute to the embodiment of institutional logics.</p> </li> </ol> <h2 id="the-future-of-ecosystem-development-seeing-and-shaping-together">The Future of Ecosystem Development: Seeing and Shaping Together</h2> <p>As we look to the future of entrepreneurial ecosystem development, our research suggests that visual imagery should play a central role. We need to move beyond the assumption that simply bringing people together creates meaningful connection and shared understanding. Instead, we should create environments where diverse actors can literally see their thoughts, assumptions, and aspirations take shape together.</p> <p>The power of visual imagery lies not just in its ability to represent complex ideas, but in its capacity to transform how we think and interact. When we draw together, we think together. When we see our ideas visualized, we see new possibilities. And when we create shared visual languages, we create the foundation for genuine collaborative action.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/posts/2024-01-23_crop_understanding_impact-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/posts/2024-01-23_crop_understanding_impact-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/posts/2024-01-23_crop_understanding_impact-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/posts/2024-01-23_crop_understanding_impact.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> A graphical representation of going from understanding EEs to thinking about collective, purposeful impact <a class="citation" href="#wurmaw24">(Wurth &amp; Mawson, 2024)</a>. </div> <h2 id="conclusion-drawing-our-way-to-better-ecosystems">Conclusion: Drawing Our Way to Better Ecosystems</h2> <p>Our research reveals that developing effective entrepreneurial ecosystems requires more than words - it requires ways of seeing and making sense together that transcend verbal communication. Visual imagery, when thoughtfully integrated into ecosystem conversations, can:</p> <ul> <li>surface and legitimize diverse perspectives,</li> <li>create powerful, persistent metaphors for complex concepts,</li> <li>facilitate alignment on shared meanings, and</li> <li>enable exploration of “distant futures” and alternative possibilities.</li> </ul> <p>As we continue to grapple with the complexity of entrepreneurial ecosystems, let’s remember that sometimes the most powerful conversations happen not just through what we say, but through what we draw, imagine, and visualize together. In the end, building better ecosystems might just require us to become better at seeing - and helping others see - the bigger picture.</p> <p>After all, when it comes to understanding complex social systems, a picture really can be worth a thousand words - or perhaps more accurately, a thousand conversations.</p> <hr/> <p><em>Below are the complete graphical illustrations (two per workshop) from which the excerpts for the paper were taken.</em></p> <swiper-container keyboard="true" navigation="true" pagination="true" pagination-clickable="true" pagination-dynamic-bullets="true" rewind="true"> <swiper-slide> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/scottish_ee_illustrations/week_01-01-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/scottish_ee_illustrations/week_01-01-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/scottish_ee_illustrations/week_01-01-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/scottish_ee_illustrations/week_01-01.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </swiper-slide> <swiper-slide> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/scottish_ee_illustrations/week_01-02-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/scottish_ee_illustrations/week_01-02-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/scottish_ee_illustrations/week_01-02-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/scottish_ee_illustrations/week_01-02.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </swiper-slide> <swiper-slide> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/scottish_ee_illustrations/week_02-01-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/scottish_ee_illustrations/week_02-01-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/scottish_ee_illustrations/week_02-01-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/scottish_ee_illustrations/week_02-01.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </swiper-slide> <swiper-slide> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/scottish_ee_illustrations/week_02-02-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/scottish_ee_illustrations/week_02-02-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/scottish_ee_illustrations/week_02-02-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/scottish_ee_illustrations/week_02-02.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </swiper-slide> <swiper-slide> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/scottish_ee_illustrations/week_03-01-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/scottish_ee_illustrations/week_03-01-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/scottish_ee_illustrations/week_03-01-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/scottish_ee_illustrations/week_03-01.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </swiper-slide> <swiper-slide> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/scottish_ee_illustrations/week_03-02-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/scottish_ee_illustrations/week_03-02-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/scottish_ee_illustrations/week_03-02-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/scottish_ee_illustrations/week_03-02.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </swiper-slide> <swiper-slide> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/scottish_ee_illustrations/week_04-01-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/scottish_ee_illustrations/week_04-01-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/scottish_ee_illustrations/week_04-01-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/scottish_ee_illustrations/week_04-01.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </swiper-slide> <swiper-slide> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/scottish_ee_illustrations/week_04-02-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/scottish_ee_illustrations/week_04-02-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/scottish_ee_illustrations/week_04-02-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/scottish_ee_illustrations/week_04-02.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </swiper-slide> </swiper-container> <p><em>You can also download the high-resolution version of each illustration here:</em></p> <p><a href="/assets/img/scottish_ee_illustrations/week_01-01.jpg" download="Workshop 1 - Illustration 1.jpg">Download Workshop 1 - Illustration 1</a> <br/> <a href="/assets/img/scottish_ee_illustrations/week_01-02.jpg" download="Workshop 1 - Illustration 2.jpg">Download Workshop 1 - Illustration 2</a> <br/> <a href="/assets/img/scottish_ee_illustrations/week_02-01.jpg" download="Workshop 2 - Illustration 1.jpg">Download Workshop 2 - Illustration 1</a> <br/> <a href="/assets/img/scottish_ee_illustrations/week_02-02.jpg" download="Workshop 2 - Illustration 2.jpg">Download Workshop 2 - Illustration 2</a> <br/> <a href="/assets/img/scottish_ee_illustrations/week_03-01.jpg" download="Workshop 3 - Illustration 1.jpg">Download Workshop 3 - Illustration 1</a> <br/> <a href="/assets/img/scottish_ee_illustrations/week_03-02.jpg" download="Workshop 3 - Illustration 2.jpg">Download Workshop 3 - Illustration 2</a> <br/> <a href="/assets/img/scottish_ee_illustrations/week_04-01.jpg" download="Workshop 4 - Illustration 1.jpg">Download Workshop 4 - Illustration 1</a> <br/> <a href="/assets/img/scottish_ee_illustrations/week_04-02.jpg" download="Workshop 4 - Illustration 2.jpg">Download Workshop 4 - Illustration 2</a> <br/></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Insights"/><category term="Publication"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Read more about our new paper published in the Journal of Business Venturing Insights.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">INSIGHT - A Systems Approach to Entrepreneurial Universities</title><link href="https://bwurth.github.io/posts/2024/insight-sbe-paper/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="INSIGHT - A Systems Approach to Entrepreneurial Universities"/><published>2024-01-23T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-01-23T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://bwurth.github.io/posts/2024/insight-sbe-paper</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://bwurth.github.io/posts/2024/insight-sbe-paper/"><![CDATA[<p><em>This post is based on research published in our paper “Not Seeing the Forest for the Trees? A Systems Approach to the Entrepreneurial University” <a class="citation" href="#wurmachow24">(Wurth et al., 2024)</a>.</em></p> <hr/> <h2 id="introduction-missing-the-forest-for-the-trees">Introduction: Missing the Forest for the Trees</h2> <p>In recent years, universities have been increasingly expected to contribute to economic development beyond their traditional missions of teaching and research. This has given rise to what we call the “entrepreneurial university” – institutions that engage in a wide range of activities from technology licensing and spin-offs to collaborative research and consulting with industry partners.</p> <p>As academics, we’ve studied these entrepreneurial activities extensively. Yet something has been missing in our approach. We’ve largely focused on individual activities, specific institutions, or isolated case studies – effectively examining the trees while missing the forest. In our recent paper <em>“Not Seeing the Forest for the Trees? A Systems Approach to the Entrepreneurial University,”</em> my colleagues Niall MacKenzie, Susan Howick, and I argue that we need a more holistic understanding of entrepreneurial universities that captures their inherent complexity and interconnectedness.</p> <h2 id="the-problem-with-current-research">The Problem with Current Research</h2> <p>The current academic literature suffers from three key limitations:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Isolated focus:</strong> Studies typically examine single activities (like licensing or spin-offs) without considering how they interact with other activities within the university.</li> <li><strong>De-contextualization:</strong> Research often fails to consider the broader ecosystem in which universities operate, treating them as isolated entities rather than parts of a larger system.</li> <li><strong>Static perspective:</strong> Most studies provide snapshot views rather than examining the dynamic evolution of entrepreneurial universities over time.</li> </ul> <p>The result is a fragmented understanding – what we refer to as “unit theories” of constituent parts without considering the wider feedback effects and implications. We’re looking at individual trees but missing how they form a complex, interconnected forest.</p> <h2 id="a-systems-thinking-approach">A Systems Thinking Approach</h2> <p>To address these limitations, we’ve developed what we call a “programmatic theory” of entrepreneurial universities using a systems thinking approach. Rather than focusing on isolated components, we’re examining how different activities, capabilities, and contextual factors interact and influence each other over time.</p> <p>Our research combines qualitative interviews with technology transfer office directors and staff from seven Scottish universities with quantitative data from various national surveys on university-industry interactions. We’ve synthesized these insights using causal loop diagrams (CLDs) – a tool from system dynamics that visualizes the interconnections and feedback loops within complex systems.</p> <h2 id="the-entrepreneurial-university-as-a-system-of-feedback-loops">The Entrepreneurial University as a System of Feedback Loops</h2> <p>So what does this systems perspective reveal? Let me walk you through some key insights from our model.</p> <h3 id="research-and-commercialization-dynamics">Research and Commercialization Dynamics</h3> <p>At the heart of our model is the relationship between research activities and commercialization. Universities conduct research, which can lead to discoveries and inventions. These may be disclosed to technology transfer offices, potentially leading to patents, licenses, and spin-off companies. The income generated from these activities is often reinvested into further research, creating a reinforcing loop.</p> <p>However, this is just the beginning. Our research shows that commercialization processes are far more complex than the linear models traditionally depicted in the literature. For instance, we found that only about a third of university spin-offs are based on disclosed and patented inventions. Many are created directly by academics without going through formal technology transfer mechanisms.</p> <h3 id="entrepreneurial-academics-as-key-agents">Entrepreneurial Academics as Key Agents</h3> <p>Our interviews revealed that most entrepreneurial activities involve a relatively small number of “entrepreneurial academics” – faculty members who actively seek opportunities to engage with industry partners. These individuals are crucial bridges between the university and external organizations.</p> <p>The total number of these entrepreneurial academics and their workload allocation define the “entrepreneurial capacity” of each university. When the amount of external engagement exceeds this capacity, universities face potential detrimental effects on their other missions. This creates balancing loops that limit growth unless universities can increase their entrepreneurial capacity. Reputation and Demand Dynamics</p> <p>Universities don’t operate in isolation – they’re embedded in ecosystems with various stakeholders, including industry partners. Our model shows how research prestige and entrepreneurial reputation influence industry demand for university collaboration.</p> <p>Companies typically follow a two-step decision process: first identifying a need for external input, then choosing their preferred academic partner. Research excellence attracts industry attention, but previous successful collaborations build entrepreneurial reputation, creating reinforcing loops that can accelerate future engagement.</p> <h3 id="supply-and-demand-stimulation">Supply and Demand Stimulation</h3> <p>Universities can grow their entrepreneurial activities through two main levers: internal supply stimulation and external demand stimulation.</p> <p>Internal stimulation involves increasing the number of entrepreneurial academics through incentives, skill development, and strategic hiring. External stimulation includes proactively engaging with industry, demonstrating expertise, and building relationships.</p> <p>Importantly, our research shows that universities must balance both approaches. Focusing on one at the expense of the other merely shifts the bottleneck rather than enabling sustainable growth.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/posts/2024-03-01_cld_highlighted.pdf-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/posts/2024-03-01_cld_highlighted.pdf-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/posts/2024-03-01_cld_highlighted.pdf-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/posts/2024-03-01_cld_highlighted.pdf" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Complete causal-loop-diagram (CLD) with references to the aggregate themes from the interviews overlaid: ‘entrepreneurial academics’ (green), ‘supply stimulation’ (brown), ‘resource allocation according to university strategy’ (yellow), ‘reputation’ (orange), ‘partnerships’ (blue), and ‘demand stimulation’ (purple). <a class="citation" href="#wurmachow24">(Wurth et al., 2024)</a>. </div> <h2 id="practical-implications-lessons-for-universities-and-policymakers">Practical Implications: Lessons for Universities and Policymakers</h2> <p>What does this systems perspective mean for university leaders and policymakers? Here are some key takeaways:</p> <h3 id="for-university-leaders">For University Leaders:</h3> <ol> <li><strong>Recognize trade-offs:</strong> Increasing entrepreneurial activities without a balanced approach risks undermining other university missions. Our model helps visualize these potential trade-offs.</li> <li><strong>Develop dynamic capabilities:</strong> Universities need capabilities that allow them to sense changes in the environment and adapt accordingly. These go beyond static resources to include organizational learning and flexibility.</li> <li><strong>Cultivate partnerships, not just transactions:</strong> Long-term relationships with industry partners yield more value than one-off interactions. Universities should transition from a contractor mindset (offering “knowledge on a market basis”) to a partnership approach.</li> <li><strong>Balance supply and demand stimulation:</strong> Growing entrepreneurial activities requires both increasing internal capacity and generating external demand. Focusing on just one creates bottlenecks.</li> </ol> <h3 id="for-policymakers">For Policymakers:</h3> <ol> <li><strong>Look beyond commercialization:</strong> Policy support should extend beyond narrow metrics like patents and licenses to encompass the broader range of entrepreneurial activities.</li> <li><strong>Support capacity building:</strong> Effective policies must help universities develop the capabilities to manage complex entrepreneurial activities while maintaining excellence in teaching and research.</li> <li><strong>Treat university engagement as a “commons”:</strong> When universities actively engage with external organizations, they benefit the entire higher education sector by demonstrating the value of academic collaboration.</li> <li><strong>Consider systemic impacts:</strong> Our model helps policymakers anticipate how interventions might affect different parts of the system, potentially revealing unintended consequences.</li> </ol> <h2 id="the-value-of-systems-thinking-in-practice">The Value of Systems Thinking in Practice</h2> <p>Let me illustrate the practical value of this approach with an example from our research. One university we studied wanted to increase its industry engagement. Initial discussions focused on marketing and promotion strategies to attract more companies. However, our systems analysis revealed that entrepreneurial academics were already at full capacity.</p> <p>Without addressing this internal constraint, additional marketing would have created frustration as academics couldn’t take on more projects. By understanding the system as a whole, the university could develop a more balanced approach – gradually increasing academic capacity while strategically growing external demand.</p> <p>This example highlights why seeing both the forest and the trees matters. Understanding individual components (trees) is necessary but insufficient. We must also grasp how they interact within the broader system (forest).</p> <h2 id="future-research-directions">Future Research Directions</h2> <p>Our work opens several promising avenues for future research:</p> <ol> <li><strong>Methodological innovation:</strong> We need approaches that can capture feedback loops and interdependencies, such as system dynamics modeling and network analysis.</li> <li><strong>Data integration:</strong> Rather than creating new datasets for each study, researchers should combine existing data to gain more comprehensive insights.</li> <li><strong>Contextual variations:</strong> How do entrepreneurial university dynamics differ across geographic and institutional contexts?</li> <li><strong>Teaching-entrepreneurship connections:</strong> Future research should explore how teaching contributes to entrepreneurial universities, particularly in developing skills and entrepreneurial mindsets among graduates.</li> </ol> <h2 id="conclusion-embracing-complexity">Conclusion: Embracing Complexity</h2> <p>In conclusion, understanding entrepreneurial universities requires embracing complexity rather than avoiding it. Our systems approach offers a more holistic perspective that reconciles existing “unit theories” into a coherent programmatic theory.</p> <p>For university leaders, this perspective enables better strategic decision-making by helping diagnose capabilities and identify leverage points for improvement. For policymakers, it provides a framework for developing more effective support mechanisms that account for interdependencies and potential unintended consequences.</p> <p>By seeing both the forest and the trees, we can unlock the full potential of entrepreneurial universities to contribute to economic development and address societal challenges.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Insights"/><category term="Publication"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Read more about our new paper published in Small Business Economics.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Venturithm joins Strathclyde Inspire Accelerator</title><link href="https://bwurth.github.io/posts/2023/news-venturithm-inspire/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Venturithm joins Strathclyde Inspire Accelerator"/><published>2023-10-28T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-10-28T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://bwurth.github.io/posts/2023/news-venturithm-inspire</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://bwurth.github.io/posts/2023/news-venturithm-inspire/"><![CDATA[<p>Venturithm Ltd is proud to announce its acceptance into the <a href="https://www.strath.ac.uk/workwithus/strathclydeinspire/">University of Strathclyde Inspire</a> accelerator programme.</p> <p>This opportunity marks an exciting reunion with the University of Strathclyde, where I received my doctoral degreee and was a lecturer at the Hunter Centre for Entrepreneurship.</p> <blockquote> <p>“Joining the Inspire Accelerator is a full-circle moment for me. I have a deep personal connection to this institution, having been a PhD student and faculty member here. I am excited to build on that experience, coupled with fresh perspectives, and work with the team on taking Venturithm to the next level.” —Bernd Wurth</p> </blockquote> <hr/> <p>Strathclyde Inspire supports entrepreneurship in all its forms across the university’s ecosystem. For Strathclyde students, staff members, or alumni, there is support for:</p> <ul> <li>exploring your entrepreneurial potential, </li> <li>your idea for a business, or </li> <li>commercialising your research,</li> </ul> <p>through the four stages of Explore, Create, Launch, and Grow.</p> <p>Based in the heart of Scotland’s first Innovation District, GCID, the investor-ready <a href="https://www.strath.ac.uk/workwithus/strathclydeinspire/">Inspire Accelerator</a> welcomes participants on a rolling basis, ensuring you can fast-track your opportunity when the time is right. Over the course of 12-18 months, you will have access to a range of support including, but not limited to one-to-one advice; funding; bespoke training opportunities; regular cohort meetings; online presence; access to alumni, industry and partner networks; support from a virtual board; commercial champions; and pitching competitions.</p> <hr/> <p>For more information about Venturithm Ltd, its participation in the University of Strathclyde Inspire Accelerator programme, and everything else we are working on, please visit <a href="https://venturithm.com">https://venturithm.com</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="News"/><category term="Venturithm"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We are grateful for the support that will accelerate our product development and go-to-market.]]></summary></entry></feed>